<!DOCTYPE ui:UiBinder SYSTEM "http://dl.google.com/gwt/DTD/xhtml.ent">
<ui:UiBinder xmlns:ui="urn:ui:com.google.gwt.uibinder"
	xmlns:g="urn:import:com.google.gwt.user.client.ui" xmlns:c="urn:import:com.google.gwt.user.cellview.client"
	xmlns:s="urn:import:org.sagebionetworks.web.client.view">

	<ui:style>
		.important {
			font-weight: bold;
		}
		
		.rowTop {
			vertical-align: top;
		}
		strong {
			font-weight: bold;
		}
		.underline {
			text-decoration: underline !important;
		}
	</ui:style>

	<g:HTMLPanel>

		<!-- start header -->
	<!-- MAIN CONTAINER -->
		<!-- HEADER -->
        <div class="color-line"></div>
        <div class="clear"></div>
    	<div class="container"> 		
			<g:SimplePanel ui:field="header" />
			
	        	<div class="span-24 notopmargin">
				<!-- end header -->

					<ul class="breadcrumbs">
						<li class="breadcrumb">
							<a href="#">Home</a>
						</li>
					</ul>

					<div class="info">

						<h2 align="center">Synapse Commons Governance Overview</h2>
						<p>Synapse operates under a complete governance process that includes
							well-documented Terms and Conditions of Use, guidelines and operating
							procedures, privacy enhancing technologies, as well as the right of
							audit and external reviews.</p>
						<p>
							<a class="link" target="_blank" href="static/governance/SageBionetworksSynapseTermsandConditionsofUse.pdf">
								<h4>Terms and Conditions of Use</h4>
							</a>
							
							The Terms and Conditions of Use document is a detailed description of
							the terms by which Synapse users must operate.  It establishes the
							use, disclaimers and limitation of liability governing the use of
							Synapse including the requirement to adhere to all laws and
							regulations to protect the privacy of participants whose data they
							use.     
						</p>
						<p>
							<a class="link" target="_blank" href="static/governance/SynapseCommonsDataUseProcedure.pdf">
								<h4>Data Use Procedure</h4>
							</a>
							Robust procedures support data contribution and use through a Tiered
							system that distinguishes Open, Restricted or Controlled data use
							based on the nature of the data and the conditions delineated by the
							data contributor. Data stored in Synapse must be de-identified
							according to
							<a class="link" target="_blank" href="http://www.hhs.gov/ocr/privacy/hipaa/understanding/index.html">HIPAA standards</a>
							. Synapse users must register before contributing or using content on
							Synapse.  Use of open or restricted data is authorized in an automated
							fashion but use of controlled data requires users to engage an ethics
							committee or institutional review board for approval of their data
							analysis plan prior to accessing the data through Synapse
						</p>
						<p>
							<a class="link" target="_blank" href="static/governance/SynapsePrivacyPolicy.pdf">
								<h4>Privacy Policy</h4>
							</a>							
							The Privacy Policy explains how Sage Bionetworks aims to protect
							personal information received in connection with Synapse from casual
							visitors and registered users.  Personal information may include: your
							name, email, or other information that identifies you personally. We
							do not require you to register to visit the Synapse website. However
							sections of the site and access to some content will be granted only
							to Registered users for research, statistics and training purposes.
						</p>
						<p>
							<h4>
								<a class="link" href="#!WikiPlace:dataAccessLevelsContent">Training</a>
							</h4>
							Tutorial material explaining how to contribute or access data within
							Synapse, including governance definitions, is available. 
						</p>
						<p>
							<h4>Governance Contact information </h4>
							We welcome feedback if you have any questions regarding our governance
							process.
							<br />
							Contact us at: <a class="link" href="mailto:act@sagebase.org">act@sagebase.org</a>
							<br />							 
							<br />
							By using Synapse you consent to these Governance policies and
							procedures.
						</p>
												
					</div>
				</div>

				<!-- start footer -->
            <div class="clear"></div>
        </div> <!-- close class="container" -->
		<g:SimplePanel ui:field="footer" />
		<!-- end footer -->

	</g:HTMLPanel>
</ui:UiBinder> 